Guide to the Edith Segal Collection on Labor Activism TAM.684
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Edith Segal Collection on Labor Activism
1918-1980
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Segal, Edith, 1902-
Segel, Shari
TAM.684
0.25 linear feet in 1 half manuscript box
The Edith Segal Collection on Labor Activism (dated 1918-1980) contains a small assortment of items created and collected by Edith Segal. Segal (1906-1997) was an American dancer, teacher, and poet from New York City. The collection contains various items related to labor activism and life in early-20th century America, and consist of a scrapbook from World War I, a pamphlet on New York Child Labor and Compulsory Education Laws (1918); a flyer for a 1936 May Day rally; a flyer for a play satirizing the Civilian Conservation Corps; an article from Home and Education (1941), a magazine for Jewish mothers and teachers; and a report from the United Workers Cooperative Colony 50th Anniversary (1977). The collection also contains German-language ephemera from the Prolet Buehne in New York City, and two drafts written by Segal, photographs of Labor Day rallies in Detroit (circa 1937-1938), and reproductions of photographs taken by Lewis W. Hine for the National Child Labor Committee.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Shari Segel in 2015; additional materials were donated in 2018. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2016.005 and 2018.089.
Arrangement
Items in the collection have been retained in their original groupings and arranged in roughly chronological order.
Biographical Note
Edith Segal (1906-1997) was an American dancer, teacher, and poet. She was born in New York's Lower East Side in 1906 to working-class Jewish immigrants. Throughout her life Segal was a committed leftist, and her work was closely tied to her political activism. A supporter of the Soviet Union, Segal formed the dance company the Red Dancers in 1929 and choreographed performances in honor of V.I. Lenin. Her other works focused on topics related civil and workers' rights as well as Jewish cultural themes. She created her most famous work Black and White in 1930, which was the first interracial dance performance in the United States. Later in her life Segal worked as a dance teacher at Camp Kinderland and published several books of poetry. She died in New York City in 1997.
Related Archival Materials
Edith Segal Papers, call number: (S) *MGZMD 122, Jerome Robbins Dance Division, New York Public Library for the Performing Arts, Dorothy and Lewis B. Cullman Center, 40 Lincoln Center Plaza, New York, NY 10023-7498
Scope and Contents
The Edith Segal Collection on Labor Activism (1918-1980) contains a small assortment of items created and collected by dancer and writer Edith Segal. These materials relate generally to labor activism and life in early-20th century America. They include a scrapbook from World War I; a pamphlet on New York Child Labor and Compulsory Education Laws (1918); flyers from a May Day Rally and a skit satirizing the Civilian Conservation Corps in the 1930s; an article from Home and Education (1941), a magazine for Jewish mothers and teachers; and a report from the United Workers Cooperative Colony 50th Anniversary (1977). The collection also includes four photographs of Labor Day rallies in Detroit (circa 1937-1938), and a folder containing reproductions of photographs taken by Lewis W. Hine for the National Child Labor Committee.
The collection contains German-language ephemera from the Prolet Buehne in New York City, and two of drafts written by Segal, which include a 1937 script for the skit "Million Dollar Baby," about a strike at the Woolworth's department store, and "I Remember Rose: A Remembrance of Rose Pastor Stokes" (circa 1980s).
Separated Materials
Issues of the publications Workers' Theatre,1931-1933 (call number PN2000 .N49 Non-circulating); New Theatre, 1933-1937 ( call number PN2000 .N49 Oversize Non-circulating); and one issue of Photo-History, July 1937 (call number AP2 .P5585 Oversize Non-circulating) have been transferred to the library collection.
Labor movement -- Political activity -- United States.; Scrapbooks.; Black-and-white photographs.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Social aspects -- United States.; Agitprop theater; Radical theater; Segel, Shari
- WWI Scrapbook, 1918-1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Flyers -- Performance and Rally, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Photographs -- Labor Marches in Detroit, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "Million Dollar Baby" by Edith Segal (Skit on the Woolworth's Strike), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "For Our Child, Our Future" in Home and Education, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- United Workers Cooperative Colony 50th Anniversary, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "I Remember Rose: A Remembrance of Rose Pastor Stokes" by Edith Segal, circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Lewis Hine Reproductions, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letter to and from Yalta Children, 1966-04 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Theater Ephemera, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 10)